如果你今天要求人们说机器人的样子，他们要么告诉你
If you ask people today to say what a robot looks like, they're either going to tell you
关于一个虚构的机器人，比如R2D2，或者他们会提到这样的制造机器人
about a fictional robot, like R2D2 or they're going to mention a manufacturing robot such
就像这里展示的一样，今天有很多这样的机器人在地球上工作，
as the one shown here and there are many many of these robots at work on the planet today,
超过100万，他们支持许多现代制造业，汽车，
more than 1 million of them and they underpin a lot of modern manufacturing, of automobiles,
电子设备，如电脑。
of electronic devices, like computers.
他们还进行了大量的物料搬运，将箱子从传送带上移开并放置
They also do a lot of material handling, moving boxes off conveyor belts and putting them
在装运纸箱时，甚至拿起装运纸箱并将它们放在托盘上
in shipping cartons, even picking up shipping cartons and putting them onto pallets and
等等。像这样的机器人代表了第一代机器人。他们真的很直接
so on. Robots such as this represent the first generation of robots. They are really direct
我们在上一节谈到的UnimationInc.创建的机器人的后代。
descendants of the robots created by Unimation Inc. that we talked about in the last section.
这是一个现代制造机器人的例子。这是我拍摄的视频
Here's an example of a modern manufacturing robot at work. This is a video that I took
在去年的机器人展览会上。我们可以看到机器人正在移动和拾取
at a robot exhibition last year. And what we can see is the robot is moving and picking
从斜坡底部的水桶中取出一块，你可以看到它们的碎片
up a piece from the bucket at the bottom of the ramp, and you can see that the pieces
都是在不同的方向，机器人有一些传感器，以便它可以确定
are all in different orientations and the robot has got some sensors so that it can determine
为了拾取物体需要采用的夹具的方向，以及
the orientation of its gripper that it needs to adopt in order to pick-up the object, and
一旦它完成了，将它移动到坡道的顶部并让它去。这个机器人是
once it has done that, moves it to the top of the ramp and lets it go. This robot is
执行无限循环从位置A拾取物品并将其放在位置B.
performing an endless loop of pick up the thing from location A and drop it at location B.
另一种机器人就是这个。这是机器人吸尘器，这是一项技术
Another type of robot is this. This is the robot vacuum cleaner and this is a technology
这是在2004年左右推出的，从那时起它们变得非常受欢迎，
that was introduced around 2004 and since that time they became enormously popular,
其中已售出1000多万件。那么我们看到的制造机器人片刻
more than 10 million of them have been sold. So the manufacturing robot that we saw a moment
以前是一项近60年的技术，其中有一百万在工作。这个
ago is a technology that's nearly 60 years old and there’s a million of them at work. This
只有十多年历史的技术已售出超过1000万件。
technology which is only just over a decade old has sold more than 10 million of them.
这些机器人如此受欢迎的原因之一是它们执行一项非常有用的任务，一项任务
One of the reasons these robots are so popular is they perform a very useful task, a task
人类不喜欢这么做，他们以非常低的价格做到这一点。原因
that human beings don't like doing so much, and they do it for a very low price. The reason
他们能够以如此低的成本制造机器人，它的计算量非常有限
that they're able to build a robot for such a low cost is it has got really limited computational
能力和机器人能够通过采用非常简单的策略来清洁地板。
capability and robots are able to clean the floor by adopting a very very simple strategy.
机器人实际上并不知道它在哪里。它的作用只是直线驱动
The robot doesn't actually know where it is. What it does is just drives in a straight
线，吸收污垢，直到它碰到障碍物并从障碍物反弹然后去
line, sucking up dirt until it hits an obstacle and bounces off the obstacle and then goes
在另一个方向。
in a different direction.
所以这张时间流逝图片显示了Roomba机器人清洁起居室的路径
So this time lapse picture here, shows the path of a Roomba robot cleaning a living room
我们可以看到它从墙壁和家具上弹开的地方。采用这个
and we can see where it's bounced off the walls and off the furniture. By adopting this
非常简单的策略，我们可以覆盖整个房间。但很明显，有些部分是
very simple strategy, we can cover the whole room. It's clear though, that some parts of
房间被遮盖很多次，房间的某些部分不经常被遮盖
the room are covered many many times and some parts of the room are covered not very often
一点都不我们可以想象扩大像这样的技术
at all. We can imagine scaling up a technology like
真空吸尘器到机器人系统，能够拿起和放下容器
that vacuum cleaner to a robot system that's able to pick up and put down containers in
一个航运港口，事实上人们已经建立了远程系统来做到这一点。
a shipping port, and in fact people have built remote systems to do this.
因此，这些机器人在位置A拿起一个集装箱，然后将它们运送到位置B.
So these robots pick up a container at location A and transport it to location B, when they
再说一遍。在制造过程中将材料从位置A移动到位置B的机器人
put it down again. Robots that move materials from location A to location B, inside manufacturing
植物现在非常普遍，这使它们与第一代植物分开
plants are now really quite common, and this separates them from the first generation of
机器人。制造机器人固定在世界上的一个地方，
robots. The manufacturing robots which are fixed at a single place in the world, the
下一代机器人能够在环境中移动。
next generation of robots are able to move within the environment.
在这里，我们看到一个叫做小狗的研究机器人，它起到了非常重要的作用
Here we see a research robot called little dog, and it played a really important role
研究我们如何计划机器人放置脚的地方以便合理地行走
in research into how we plan where robots place their feet in order to walk competently
在非常粗糙和不平坦的地形。
over very rough and uneven terrain.
在这里，我们看到小狗的大哥哥，逻辑上称为大狗，这是一个机器人
Here we see the big brother of little dog, logically called big dog, and this is a robot
在现实的室外，它可以在非常崎岖的地形上承载相当大的有效载荷
that's able to carry quite a large payload over very rough terrain in realistic outdoor
环境。在这里，我们看到了这个机器人走过的稳定性的演示
environments. Here we see a demonstration of the stability of this robot walking over
冰和被踢在一边，能够恢复平衡，继续走路。
ice and being kicked in the side and able to recover its balance and keep on walking.
我们再一次看到它能够从非常困难的情况中恢复过来的精彩演示。
Once again we can see a wonderful demonstration of its ability to recover from very very difficult situations.
除了轮子和腿，机器人也可以飞行，人们已经证明了
In addition to wheels and legs, robots can also fly and people have demonstrated very
像左翼的全球鹰这样的大型飞行机器人真的很小
large scale flying robots like the Global Hawk here on the left and really, really small
飞行机器人显示在右侧。那么机器人的定义是什么？一个定义
flying robots are shown here on the right. So what's the definition of a robot? A definition
我喜欢很多并且我认为它实际上非常有用，即使它可能也是如此
that I like a lot and I think is actually very very useful, even though it's perhaps
有点简单，它是一台将东西从A移动到B的机器。现在，它是可编程的
a little simple is it's a machine that moves things from A to B. Now, it's a programmable
因此我们可以控制位置A和位置B以及位置A
machine so we can control the location A and the location B and perhaps the location A
是机器人从其传感器中获取的信息的函数。但最简单的
is a function of information that the robot picks up from its sensors. But in the simplest
例如，机器人是将东西从A移动到B的机器。
case, a robot is a machine that moves things from A to B.
从移动机器人，例如那些有轮子或腿或螺旋桨并可以飞行的机器人，
From mobile robots such as those that have got wheels or legs or propellers and can fly,
我们可以将其视为从位置A自动移动到位置的机器
we can think of it as a machine that moves automatically from location A to location
B.我喜欢的机器人的高级别，更复杂的定义是面向目标的
B. A high level, a more complex definition of a robot that I like is it is a goal-oriented
可以感知，计划和行动的机器，这个短语捕获，我认为这四个真的
machine that can sense, plan and act, and this phrase catches, I think the four really
机器人的关键元素。首先，它是一台拥有的机器
key elements of a robot. The first thing is, it's a machine that has
一个目标。它想要实现某些东西，它希望从一个产品中实现
a goal. There's something that it wants to achieve, it wants to deliver itself from one
放在另一个地方，或者它想把东西从一个地方搬到另一个地方，这就是它
place to another or it wants to move something from one place to another, so that is its
目标。
goal.
在制造机器人的例子中，我们看到它能够感知到哪里
In the example of the manufacturing robot, we saw that it was able to sense where are
它想要拾取的白色物体。我们看到一只小狗走路机器人，它
the white objects that it wanted to pick-up. We saw with a little dog walking robot, it
能够感知其环境的形状，以确定它的脚应该在哪里
was able to sense the shape of its environment in order to determine where its feet should
那就把我们带到下一部分，就是计划。一旦机器人感觉到了
go and that brings us then to the next part, that is to plan. So once the robot has sensed
它在哪里并感知到它正在移动的环境，然后它
where it is and sensed something about the environment in which it's moving, then it
制定计划，让机器人更接近目标，并按顺序创建计划
makes a plan to bring the robot closer to its goal and once it's created a plan in order
为了更接近目标，它就会行动起来。
to move closer to its goal, then it acts.
它移动轮子，移动腿，它按顺序改变螺旋桨的速度
It moves the wheels, it moves the legs, it changes the speed on the propellers, in order
让机器人更接近目标。并且它不断重复这三个动作。
for the robot to get closer towards the goal. And it repeats these three actions continuously.
它感觉到，它计划，它的行为。它再次感知世界的状态，并更新它
It senses, it plans, it acts. It senses the state of the world again and it updates its
计划，然后它的行为更多，依此类推，直到达到目标。有什么特点
plan and then it acts a bit more and so on until it reaches the goal. What are the characteristics
机器人？为什么机器人对我们有用？嗯，他们有许多优点。首先
of robots? Why are robots useful to us? Well, they have a number of merits. First of all
机器人非常一致，他们一直关注，不像人类。
robots are very consistent, they pay attention all the time, unlike human beings.
机器人也非常准确。我们之前看到的制造机器人能够定位
Robots are also very accurate. The manufacturing robots that we saw earlier are able to position
每次执行时，机器人的末端精确到几分之一毫米
the end of the robot to an accuracy of a fraction of a millimeter, every single time they perform
操作，他们也非常非常可靠。他们可以24点到7点工作。他们没有
the operation and they're also very, very reliable. They can work 24 by 7. They don't
甚至需要打开灯才能完成他们的工作。所以这意味着机器人能够
even need the lights on in order to do their job. So this means that robots are able to
做一些人们做不到的事情。他们可以进入太空，他们可以深入
do a number of things that people can't do. They can go into space, they can go deep into
人类无法生存的海洋。他们也做那些事情
the oceans where human beings are just not able to survive. They also do things that
人类不会这样做。这些工作无聊或乏味。
human beings won't do. These are jobs that are boring or dull.
而且越来越多的农业和制造业都有很多低技能工作
And increasingly there are a lot of low-skill jobs in agriculture and in manufacturing where
很难找到愿意做这项工作的人。这些都是人类的工作
it's very difficult to find human beings willing to do that work. These are jobs human beings
现在考虑在他们之下，不会做。现在机器人将进入这项工作
now consider are beneath them and won't do. Now robots are going to move into that job
真空。最后，机器人做了人们不应该做的事情。他们可以完成工作
vacuum. And finally, robots do things that people shouldn't do. They can perform jobs
这是危险的，不健康的或危险的，也就是说，机器人会让人们摆脱伤害
that are dangerous, unhealthy or risky, that is, the robots take people out of harm's way
而且我认为这是机器人可以做的非常棒的事情。
and I think that's a very great thing that robots can do.
人们经常使用“肮脏，沉闷和危险”的表达来反映这三个类别
People often use the expression, 'dirty, dull and dangerous' to reflect the three classes
机器人比人类有相当大优势的工作。肮脏而危险
of jobs where robots have considerable advantage over human beings. The dirty and dangerous
工作是人类不应该做的工作，枯燥的工作是人类的工作
jobs are the ones that human beings shouldn't do and the dull jobs are the ones that human
众生不想做。
beings don't want to do.